Inventory of the William J. Casey papers
Hoover Institution Archives
William J. Casey papers
1913-1996
99003
Hoover Institution Archives
624 manuscript boxes, 2 card file boxes, 9 oversize boxes, 1 cubic foot box, 2 motion picture films (265.6 linear feet)
Correspondence, speeches and writings, diaries, memoranda, reports, hearing transcripts, legal and financial papers, printed matter, photographs, and memorabilia relating to American domestic and foreign policy, especially during the presidential administrations of Richard M. Nixon and Ronald Reagan; American intelligence operations from World War II on; and the 1980 presidential campaign of Ronald Reagan. Digital copies of select records also available at https://digitalcollections.hoover.org.
Casey, William J.
Access
Collection is open for research. Digital copies of select records also available at https://digitalcollections.hoover.org.
Use copies of some videorecordings in this collection are available for immediate access. To listen to sound recordings or to view other videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1999.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical Note
1913 March 13 Born, Elmhurst, Long Island, New York
1934 B.S., Fordham University
1937 J.D., St. John's University. Admitted to New York bar
1941 Married Sophia Kurz
1943-1945 Member, Office of Strategic Services, stationed in London
1950 Founder, Institute for Business Planning. Subsequently author of a series of its reference publications on business law
1957-1971 Partner, Hall, Casey, Dickler and Howley law firm
1966 Unsuccessful candidate for Congress, New York
1969-1970 Member, Presidential Task Force on International Development
1971-1973 Chairman, Securities and Exchange Commission
1973-1974 Under secretary of state for economic affairs
1973-1975 Member, Commission on the Organization of the Government for the Conduct of Foreign Policy
1974-1976 President and chairman, Export-Import Bank of the United States
1976 Author, Where and How the War Was Fought: An Armchair Tour of the American Revolution
1976-1977 Member, President's Foreign Intelligence Advisory Board Chairman, Small Business Administration Task Force on Venture and Equity Capital for Small Business
1976-1981 Member, Rogers and Wells law firm
1980 Director, Ronald Reagan presidential election campaign
1980-1981 Chairman, Presidential Transition Team
1981-1987 Director, Central Intelligence Agency
1987 May 6 Died, Glen Cove, New York
1988 Author, The Secret War against Hitler (published posthumously)
1989 Author, Scouting the Future: The Public Speeches of William J. Casey (published posthumously)
Scope and Content of Collection
William J. Casey held a succession of high-level positions in the executive branch of the United States government during the presidential administrations of Richard M. Nixon, Gerald R. Ford and Ronald Reagan, culminating in service as Reagan's director of the Central Intelligence Agency. Although his papers do not include official government records, they do contain personal use copies of unclassified official documents and unofficial correspondence that reflect formulation of government policy during the Nixon, Ford and Reagan administrations, with particular reference to the agencies which Casey headed and to the commissions on which he served.
The collection is organized into series that for the most part correspond to successive positions held by Casey or to other distinct periods in his life. Each such series contains papers created or accumulated by Casey during that period of his life. In general this conforms with the manner in which the papers were maintained during Casey's lifetime. Series based on governmental offices include: TASK FORCE ON INTERNATIONAL DEVELOPMENT (1969-1970) FILE; SECURITIES AND EXCHANGE COMMISSION (1971-1973) FILE; DEPARTMENT OF STATE (1973-1974) FILE; COMMISSION ON THE ORGANIZATION OF THE GOVERNMENT FOR THE CONDUCT OF FOREIGN POLICY (1973-1975) FILE; EXPORT-IMPORT BANK (1974-1976) FILE; FOREIGN INTELLIGENCE ADVISORY BOARD (1976-1977) FILE; TASK FORCE ON VENTURE AND EQUITY CAPITAL FOR SMALL BUSINESS (1976-1977) FILE; and CENTRAL INTELLIGENCE AGENCY (1981-1987) FILE.
Series constituted on the basis of service in a particular government position share a general similarity in arrangement. Typically each has a Speeches and Engagements subseries, arranged chronologically by event and including speeches as well as correspondence and meeting and background material related to the event in question; a Correspondence subseries, arranged alphabetically by name of correspondent; a Publicity subseries containing press coverage of Casey and preparatory material for and transcripts of interviews granted to the media; and a Subject File subseries, arranged alphabetically by topic. Subject files frequently include substantive correspondence and unpublished memoranda and reports as well as printed matter. Once again, subseries arrangement generally conforms to the arrangement of papers maintained during Casey's lifetime.
Another variety of subseries requires some explanation. Casey was a controversial figure throughout his government service. He was the subject of numerous investigations by Congressional committees, some in conjunction with confirmation hearings for a new office and some not. During the Nixon administration the investigations centered on the International Telephone and Telegraph Corporation and Robert Vesco affairs. During the Reagan administration they concerned Casey's own financial affairs, the appointment and resignation of Max Hugel as deputy director of the Central Intelligence Agency, and the theft of Jimmy Carter briefing papers during the 1980 presidential election campaign. Casey successfully weathered all investigations and confirmation hearings. The voluminous materials accumulated during these proceedings make up several subseries. From December 1986 until his death in May 1987, Casey was incapacitated by illness. There is thus little in the collection aside from press coverage relating to the Iran-Contra investigation of this period.
In addition to series formed on the basis of government office, there are three series based explicitly on political activity: CASEY FOR CONGRESS COMMITTEE (1966) FILE, dealing with Casey's lone, and unsuccessful, bid for electoral office; REAGAN/BUSH CAMPAIGN (1980) FILE, in which Casey figured as campaign manager; and PRESIDENTIAL TRANSITION TEAM (1980-1981) FILE. Casey was a lifelong Republican, and material related to party affairs and to other elections may be found in the Correspondence and Subject File subseries of other series as well.
Chronologically, the earliest series is the OFFICE OF STRATEGIC SERVICES (1943-1945) FILE. Although it is also the smallest series, it is notable in marking the beginning of Casey's long involvement with intelligence. In addition to the FOREIGN INTELLIGENCE ADVISORY BOARD and CENTRAL INTELLIGENCE AGENCY series, this interest is reflected in other series, and especially in Speeches and Engagements and Subject File subseries relating to activities of the Veterans of the O.S.S.
One series, CASEY FOUNDATION (1967-1977) FILE, is devoted to a philanthropic organization established by Casey. He was involved in many other philanthropic activities, which are documented in the Subject File subseries of various series. Some philanthropies were associated with the Roman Catholic Church, of which Casey was a lifelong member. His involvement with the International Rescue Committee was especially notable, and entries under the Committee will be found in several subject files.
Two large series deal with periods of Casey's life when he did not hold public office: PRE-GOVERNMENT CAREER (1945-1971) FILE and, coinciding with the Democratic Carter administration, PRIVATE LIFE (1976-1981) FILE. Casey's activities as a lawyer and as a businessman come to the fore here, although there are reflections of them in other series as well. Among a multitude of interests were business law publishing, tax and estate law, continuing legal education, the legal profession, public policy centers, the securities industry, Long Island civic activism, economic implications of technological advances, and entrepreneurship, as well as continuing preoccupation with politics and foreign policy.
Chronologically the last series are FINAL ILLNESS AND DEATH (1986-1987) FILE and CASEY MEMORIAL FUND (1987-1988) FILE.
Three series cut across chronological periods. WRITINGS is the most important of these. It includes Casey's published writings, together with drafts and related correspondence and background materials. Besides numerous publications in the field of business law, Casey was the author of two books, Where and How the War Was Fought, inspired by the American Revolution Bicentennial; and the posthumously published The Secret War against Hitler, in which he drew on his own experiences in the Office of Strategic Services. There are very extensive drafts of the latter work, composition of which was long drawn-out and which was extensively revised, and a large volume of research material assembled for the writing project. AUDIOVISUAL MATERIAL is cross-referenced with related textual material. PRINTED MATTER consists of Casey's personal copies of printed material accessible elsewhere.
The William J. Casey papers were acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives from Sophia Kurz Casey in 1999.
Scope and Content of Collection Addendum
Arrangement of the William J. Casey papers into the 20 series described above (Boxes 1-427) was completed in 2002. Subsequently another large body of papers (Boxes 428-636) was received. These papers have been arranged into another 21 series, of which 19 are simply addenda to series in the first body of material. There is, in fact, an ADDENDUM series for each of the initial 20 series except for TASK FORCE ON INTERNATIONAL DEVELOPMENT (1969-1970) FILE. Within each ADDENDUM series, arrangement by subseries is similar to that in the corresponding initial series. This reflects the fact that the material in the second body of papers is in general very similar to the material in the first body. For example, most alphabetically filed correspondence for letters A-Q from Casey's Central Intelligence Agency years arrived in the first body of material and is to be found in the CENTRAL INTELLIGENCE AGENCY series, while most alphabetical correspondence from the same period for letters R-Z arrived in the second body and is to be found in the CENTRAL INTELLIGENCE AGENCY ADDENDUM series. There are similar instances of divided filing sequences elsewhere. The researcher who has identified one of the first 20 series as being of interest will also want to consult the corresponding ADDENDUM series.
There are two unique series in the ADDENDUM portion of the Casey papers. The first is a small EARLY LIFE (1913-1943) FILE series containing material documenting Casey's life prior to his entry into the Office of Strategic Services. The second is a MEMORABILIA series of plaques, awards, diplomas, certificates, and assorted three-dimensional objects from all periods of his life.
Alternate Forms Available
Digital copies of select records also available at https://digitalcollections.hoover.org.
Export-Import Bank of the United States.; Nixon, Richard M. (Richard Milhous), 1913-1994.; Reagan, Ronald.; United States. Central Intelligence Agency.; United States. Department of State.; United States. Office of Strategic Services.; United States. Securities and Exchange Commission.; Finance, Public--United States.; Intelligence service--United States.; Presidents--United States--Election--1980.; Secret service--United States.; United States--Foreign relations--1969-1974.; United States--Foreign relations--1981-1989.; United States--Politics and government--1969-1974.; United States--Politics and government--1981-1989.; World War, 1939-1945--Secret service.
- WRITINGS, 1951-1988 (Boxes 1-73)
  Scope and Contents note
  Published writings by Casey and writings by Casey intended for publication. Speeches can be found in Speeches and Engagements subseries of other series
  - "How to Use Charitable and Trust Foundations,", 1951 April 27 (Box-folder 1: 1)
  - "Corporate Organization and Reorganization," Tulane Tax Institute 4th Annual Proceedings, 1955 (Box-folder 1: 2)
    Printed copies
  - "Use of Company Stock in Employee Benefit Plans," New York University Institute on Federal Taxation 14th Annual Proceedings, 1956 (Box-folder 1: 3)
  - "Is Your Company Overlooking Tax Advantages in Management Decisions?" Dun's Review and Modern Industry, 1957 March (Box-folder 1: 4)
    Typescript, printed copies, and correspondence
  - Real Estate Investments and How to Make Them, 1958 (Box-folder 1: 5)
    Printed copy
  - Pay Planning, 1959? (Box-folder 1: 6, Box-folder 2: 1)
    Typescript
  - Tax Shelter in Real Estate, 2nd edition, 1959 (Box-folder 2: 2)
  - "What Price Employee Security?" Dun's Review and Modern Industry, 1959 April
    - Typescripts, galley proofs, notes, working materials and correspondence (Box-folder 2: 3)
    - Printed copies (Box-folder 2: 4-5)
  - Forms of Business Agreements and Resolutions, Volume I, 1962? (Box-folder 3: 1-2)
  - How to Buy and Sell Land, 1962 (Box-folder 3: 3)
  - How to Raise the Money You Need to Start, Run, or Expand a Business, 1962 (Box-folder 3: 4)
  - Forms of Wills, Trusts, and Family Agreements, 1963?
    - Volume I (Box-folder 3: 5)
    - Volume I (contd.) (Box-folder 4: 1)
    - Volume II (Box-folder 4: 2-3)
  - Tax Control, 1963?
    - Volume I (Box-folder 4: 4)
    - Volume I (contd.) (Box-folder 5: 1)
    - Volume II (Box-folder 5: 2-3)
  - "How Income Reorganization Can Liquefy and Even Create an Estate," C.L.U. Journal, 1963 Fall (Box-folder 5: 4)
    Typescript and correspondence
  - Tax Shelter in Real Estate, 3rd edition, 1964 (Box-folder 5: 5)
  - Forms of Business Agreements with Tax Ideas, 2nd edition, 1965 (Box-folder 6: 1)
  - Lawyer's Desk Book, 1965 (Box-folder 6: 2)
  - Real Estate, printed copy, 1965? (Box-folder 7: 1)
  - Real Estate Investments and How to Make Them, revised edition, 1965 (Box-folder 7: 2)
  - "Viet Nam," Long Island Catholic, 1966 June 9 (Box-folder 7: 3)
  - How to Build and Preserve Executive Wealth: The Truth about Probate and Family Financial Planning, 1967 (Box-folder 7: 4)
  - How to Build and Preserve Executive Wealth: The Truth about Probate and Family Financial Planning, 1967 (Box-folder 8: 1)
    Printed copies (contd.)
  - Tax Planning Desk Book, 3rd edition, 1967 (Box-folder 8: 2)
  - Corporate Planning, printed copy, 1968? (Box-folder 8: 3-4)
  - Tax Tested Forms of Business Agreements and Resolutions, printed copy, 1969?
    - Volume I (Box-folder 9: 1-2)
    - Volume II (Box-folder 9: 3-4)
  - "Huge Responsibilities Await the Investment Business in the Coming Decade: Many Changes in Store," [National Securities Traders Association publication], 1971 (Box-folder 9: 5)
  - Pay Planning, Volume II, 1971 (Box-folder 10: 1-2)
  - "Disclosure: The Best Protection for the Corporation as Well as the Investor," American Society of Corporate Secretaries 26th National Conference Report, 1972 (Box-folder 10: 3)
    Printed copy.
  - "The Securities Bar and the Securities Laws," New York State Bar Association Annual Meeting Proceedings, 1972 (Box-folder 10: 4)
  - How to Use Tax-Free and Tax-Sheltered Investments to Pyramid Your Capital: The IBP Encyclopedia of Taxwise Profit-Making Investments, revised edition, 1973 (Box-folder 10: 5)
  - Pay Planning, Volume I, 1973 (Box-folder 11: 1-2)
  - Tax Planning, 1973
    - Volume I (Box-folder 11: 3-4)
    - Volume II (Box-folder 11: 5)
    - Volume II (contd.) (Box-folder 12: 1)
  - "Prospects and Policy on East-West Trade," Department of State Bulletin, 1973 May 21 (Box-folder 12: 2)
    Printed copies.
  - "International Cooperation on Energy," Department of State Bulletin, 1973 July 9 (Box-folder 12: 3)
  - "Department Opposes Proposals for Unilateral Reduction of U.S. Troop Levels in Europe," Department of State Bulletin, 1973 August 6 (Box-folder 12: 4)
  - "Science and Technology and World Economic Affairs," Department of State Bulletin, 1973 November 19 (Box-folder 12: 5)
  - "A Comprehensive Development Policy for the United States," Department of State Bulletin, 1973 December 3 (Box-folder 12: 6)
  - The Clandestine War in Europe, 1942-1945 (pamphlet), 1974 (Box-folder 12: 7-9)
  - The Clandestine War in Europe, 1942-1945 (pamphlet), 1974 (Box-folder 13: 1-3)
  - "Technology Exchange with the USSR: Current Status and Outlook," Research Management, 1974 July (Box-folder 13: 4)
  - "The New Eximbank," American Banker, 1975 March (Box-folder 13: 5)
  - "Keynote Address to the Fordham Corporate Law Institute," Fordham University Corporate Law Institute Annual Proceedings, 1976 (Box-folder 13: 6-7)
  - Where and How the War Was Fought: An Armchair Tour of the American Revolution, 1976
    - Typescript (Box-folder 14: 1-3)
    - Maps (Box-folder 14: 4)
    - Galley proofs (Box-folder 15: 1-3)
    - Galley proofs (contd.) (Box-folder 16: 1)
    - Page proofs (Box-folder 16: 2-3)
    - Bibliographies (Box-folder 16: 4)
    - Working materials (Box-folder 16: 5)
    - Reviews (Box-folder 16: 6)
    - Book mailing lists (Box-folder 16: 7)
    - Publisher's correspondence and financial records (Box-folder 17: 1)
    - General correspondence (Box-folder 17: 2-3)
  - "How to Deal with the Government," Boardroom Reports, 1976 April 30 (Box-folder 17: 4)
  - "A New Look at Municipal Bonds: Disclosure Responsibilities in the Municipal Bond Market" (with Owen T. Smith), St. John's Law Review, 1976 Summer
    - Typescript drafts (Box-folder 17: 5)
    - Galley proofs and working material (Box-folder 17: 6)
    - Printed copies (Box-folder 18: 1-4)
    - Printed copies (contd.) (Box-folder 19: 1-2)
  - Untitled article on estate planning, 1976 June 30 (Box-folder 19: 3)
    Typescript, working materials, and letter
  - "Energy and National Security," in Frank N. Trager, ed., Oil, Divestiture and National Security, 1977
    - Typescript drafts (Box-folder 19: 4)
    - Printed copies (Box-folder 19: 5)
    - Printed copies (contd.) (Box-folder 20: 1-4)
    - Printed copies (contd.) (Box-folder 21: 1)
  - "SEC Rules 144 and 146 Revisited," Brooklyn Law Review, 1977 Spring
    - Typescript drafts (Box-folder 21: 2-6)
    - Typescript drafts (contd.) (Box-folder 22: 1-3)
    - Galley proofs and page proofs (Box-folder 22: 4)
    - Printed copies (Box-folder 22: 5-6)
    - Printed copies (contd.) (Box-folder 23: 1-5)
    - Printed copies (contd.) (Box-folder 24: 1-2)
    - Working materials (Box-folder 24: 3-5)
    - Correspondence (Box-folder 25: 1)
  - "Estate Planning through Investment Strategy," Institute on Estate Planning 12th Annual Proceedings, 1978 (Box-folder 25: 2-4)
  - "The Myth of the Rogue Elephant Interred" (re Central Intelligence Agency), 1978 June 2 (Box-folder 25: 5)
  - "Leonard W. Hall, R.I.P.," National Review, 1979 June 22 (Box-folder 25: 6)
  - Review of Milton Gould, The Witness Who Spoke with God, 1979 June 27 (Box-folder 25: 7)
    Holograph, typescript, and letters
  - "War Behind the Lines," Studies in Intelligence, 1982 Winter (Box-folder 25: 8)
  - What We Face (pamphlet), 1983 (Box-folder 25: 9-10)
  - "Regroup to Check the Soviet Thrust," Wall Street Journal, 1983 April 22 (Box-folder 25: 11)
    Printed copies and letters
  - "Covert Action," typescript, 1983 May 12 (Box-folder 25: 12)
  - "The Threat," Leaders, 1983 July-August-September (Box-folder 25: 13)
    Typescripts and correspondence
  - "The Threat and the Need for Intelligence," Signal, 1983 October (Box-folder 25: 14)
    Typescripts, printed copy, and correspondence
  - "The Health of U.S. Intelligence," Signal, 1984 May (Box-folder 26: 1)
  - "The Other Side of the Coin," Leaders, 1984 July-August-September (Box-folder 26: 2)
  - "Protecting Our Secrets: Renewing the Commitment," Signal, 1985 May (Box-folder 26: 3)
    Printed copy and letter
  - "The Eroding Balance,", 1986 March 14 (Box-folder 26: 4)
    Typescripts and letters
  - Untitled article on imagery, Signal, 1986 May (Box-folder 26: 5)
    Typescript and letter
  - "Scouting the Future," Presidential Studies Quarterly, 1986 Summer (Box-folder 26: 6-7)
  - The Secret War against Hitler, 1988
    This posthumously published work was extensively rewritten and reorganized over a number of years
    - Drafts
      Holographs and typescripts
      - 1970 (Box-folder 26: 8)
        Prospectus. "The Hidden Struggle for Europe"
      - 1976
        - Comprehensive versions (Box-folder 26: 9)
        - Comprehensive versions (contd.) (Box-folder 27: 1-3)
        - Individual chapters
          - Preface (Box-folder 27: 4)
          - "Atoms, Beams, Rockets and Robots" (Box-folder 28: 1)
          - "Beams and Rockets" (Box-folder 28: 2)
          - "Breakers" (Box-folder 28: 3)
          - "Building French Resistance" (Box-folder 28: 4)
          - "Building Resistance Forces" (Box-folder 28: 5)
          - "Easy Road to Victory" (Box-folder 28: 6)
          - "From the Riviera to Paris" (Box-folder 28: 7)
          - "German Nuclear Threat" (Box-folder 28: 8)
          - "A German Nuclear Weapon" (Box-folder 28: 9)
          - "The Grand Deception" (Box-folder 28: 10)
          - "The Grand Deception" (contd.) (Box-folder 29: 1-2)
          - "Intelligence" (Box-folder 29: 3)
          - "Intelligence for Normandy" (Box-folder 29: 4)
          - "Intelligence for Overlord" (Box-folder 29: 5)
          - "Landings and Breakout" (Box-folder 29: 6)
          - "Liberation of France" (Box-folder 29: 7)
          - "Links with the Continent" (Box-folder 29: 8)
          - "Machinery for Covert War" (Box-folder 29: 9)
          - "Normandy" (Box-folder 30: 1-2)
          - "OSS in the Liberation of France" (Box-folder 30: 3)
          - "OSS in the Penetration of Germany" (Box-folder 30: 4)
          - "Penetration of Germany" (Box-folder 30: 5)
          - "Preparation for Overlord" (Box-folder 30: 6)
          - "Race for a Nuclear Weapon" (Box-folder 30: 7)
          - "Race for the Bomb" (Box-folder 30: 8-9)
          - "Resistance Builds" (Box-folder 31: 1-3)
          - "Robots and Rockets" (Box-folder 31: 4)
          - "Secret Operations" (Box-folder 31: 5)
          - "Sources" (Box-folder 31: 6)
          - "Southern France" (Box-folder 31: 7)
          - "Sunday's Work" (Box-folder 31: 8)
          - "Unconditional Surrender" (Box-folder 32: 1)
          - "Washington" (Box-folder 32: 2)
          - "Words as Weapons" (Box-folder 32: 3)
          - Untitled and fragments (Box-folder 32: 4-7)
      - 1977, individual chapters
        - "Anvil" (Box-folder 33: 1)
        - "Atoms, Beams, Rockets and Robots" (Box-folder 33: 2)
        - "Dealing with the Enemy" (Box-folder 33: 3)
        - "Eyes and Ears Behind the Wall" (Box-folder 33: 4-5)
        - "The Grand Deception" (Box-folder 33: 6)
        - "London" (Box-folder 33: 7-8)
        - "On to Germany" (Box-folder 33: 9-10)
        - "Overlord" (Box-folder 34: 1-2)
        - "Penetration of Germany" (Box-folder 34: 3-4)
        - "Resistance Support for Overlord" (Box-folder 34: 5-6)